<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-28T11:22:46+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Psychosis and schizophrenia</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychosis and schizophrenia"/><published>2025-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychosis/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>This seminar explores psychotic experiences and schizophrenia. It combines real-world narratives, clinical tools, and scientific models to promote understanding and effective care strategies. Participants will learn to identify red flags, communicate compassionately, and support recovery in individuals experiencing psychosis.</p> <p>🔗 <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/lyra_psychosis.html">HTML Presentation</a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="psychosis-definition--types">Psychosis: Definition &amp; Types</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Psychotic experiences</strong>: Disruptions in perception, cognition, and reality monitoring.</li> <li><strong>Core phenomena</strong>: <ul> <li>Hallucinations</li> <li>Delusions</li> <li>Disorganized speech or behavior</li> <li>Thought insertion and passivity experiences</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Associated disorders</strong>: Schizophrenia spectrum, mood disorders with psychotic features, substance-induced psychosis</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="diagnosis--classification">Diagnosis &amp; Classification</h2> <ul> <li><strong>DSM-5 Criteria for Schizophrenia</strong>: <ul> <li>Two or more core symptoms for at least one month</li> <li>Functional impairment and chronicity (6+ months total)</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>ICD-10 vs ICD-11</strong>: <ul> <li>ICD-11 eliminates subtypes</li> <li>New symptom specifiers and clearer course patterns</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Syndrome vs. diagnosis</strong>: Psychosis is a transdiagnostic state, not a single disease</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="course--epidemiology">Course &amp; Epidemiology</h2> <ul> <li>Onset: Adolescence to early adulthood (earlier in males)</li> <li>Prevalence: ~0.5% globally</li> <li>Course: <ul> <li>Prodrome → first episode → variable outcomes</li> <li>Recovery, relapse, or chronic course</li> </ul> </li> <li>Better prognosis with early detection, support, and treatment</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="causes--risk-factors">Causes &amp; Risk Factors</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Biopsychosocial framework</strong>: <ul> <li><strong>Genetic</strong>: Family history increases risk</li> <li><strong>Environmental</strong>: Trauma, urbanicity, substance use (esp. cannabis)</li> <li><strong>Neurodevelopmental</strong>: Obstetric complications</li> <li><strong>Models</strong>: <ul> <li>Diathesis-stress</li> <li>Predictive coding failures</li> <li>Neurodevelopmental cascade</li> <li>Cognitive misattribution theories</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="detection--assessment">Detection &amp; Assessment</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Red flags</strong>: <ul> <li>Social withdrawal, odd beliefs, suspiciousness, functional decline</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Tools</strong>: <ul> <li>Structured interviews (e.g. PANSS, CAPS, PDI, BPRS)</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Clinical assessment</strong>: <ul> <li>Emphasis on insight, affect, and reality testing</li> <li>Early digital screening tools show promise</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="communication-strategies">Communication Strategies</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Principles</strong>: <ul> <li>Validate emotions, not delusions</li> <li>Maintain calm, non-confrontational stance</li> <li>Respect autonomy and foster collaboration</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Digital care</strong>: <ul> <li>Extra focus on tone, predictability, grounding</li> <li>Document risk carefully</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="evidence-based-treatments">Evidence-Based Treatments</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Multimodal care</strong>: <ul> <li>Antipsychotic medication</li> <li>CBT for psychosis (CBTp)</li> <li>Family interventions</li> <li>Supported employment and housing</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Recovery framework</strong>: <ul> <li>Hope, empowerment, shared decision-making</li> <li>Seamless transitions and outpatient integration</li> <li>Peer support and case management</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="case-studies">Case Studies</h2> <ul> <li><strong>The Suspicious Neighbor</strong>: Early paranoia, responsive to early intervention</li> <li><strong>Voices on the Line</strong>: Acute psychosis during crisis, role of decompensation</li> <li><strong>The Impostor Family</strong>: Delusional misidentification linked to trauma</li> <li><strong>The Silent Withdrawal</strong>: Gradual disengagement, missed early signs</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="summary--reflections">Summary &amp; Reflections</h2> <ul> <li>Psychosis reflects breakdowns in perception and cognition</li> <li>Effective detection and care require curiosity, compassion, and coordination</li> <li>Integrating biological and lived perspectives is key to reducing stigma and supporting healing</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li>🎞️ <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/lyra_psychosis.html">Lyra Seminar Presentation (Reveal.js)</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Veith Weilnhammer</name></author><category term="consciousness"/><category term="perception"/><category term="inference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lyra Health Seminar]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploration and exploitation in perception</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploration and exploitation in perception"/><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Perception involves a tradeoff between <strong>exploration</strong> — where the brain samples new information — and <strong>exploitation</strong> — where the brain relies on prior knowledge and expectations. Exploration makes perception sensitive to change but makes it vulnerable to ambiguity and noise. Knowledge about the world can help deal with ambiguity but increases the risk of circular inferences. Adaptive perception thus requires a balance between exploration and exploitation.</p> <p>Our research shows that the brain solves this problem by alternating between two functional modes: an <strong>external mode</strong>, where perception is determined by sensory inputs, and an <strong>internal mode</strong>, where perception is shaped by knowledge and memory. These fluctuations reflect a fundamental cognitive strategy: switching between information-seeking (exploration) and belief-based inference (exploitation). We show that this dynamic balance can break down in psychotic states, offering a mechanistic explanation for hallucinations and delusions.</p> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <h3 id="dynamic-explore-exploit-fluctuations">Dynamic Explore-Exploit Fluctuations</h3> <p>Analyzing behavioral data from large-scale experiments, we found that perception fluctuates between an <strong>external, exploratory mode</strong> (high accuracy, driven by current input) and an <strong>internal, exploitative mode</strong> (strong reliance on perceptual history). These dynamics help balance sensitivity to new information with the ability to have stable and robust perceptual experiences, even when sensory signals are ambiguous and noisy.</p> <h3 id="nmdar-hypofunction-disrupts-the-balance">NMDAR Hypofunction Disrupts the Balance</h3> <p>Pharmacological manipulation with <strong>S-ketamine</strong>, which blocks NMDA receptors, shifts the brain into a prolonged external (explorative) mode. This exposes perception to the destabilizing effects of noise and ambiguity and may cause people to build models of the world that don’t align with reality. We replicated the effect of NMDAR antagonism on mode in people living with schizophrenia, a diagnosis often associated with NMDAR hypofunction. These results point to a causal link between NMDAR neurotransmission, mode switching, and psychotic symptoms.</p> <h3 id="internal-predictions-and-false-percepts">Internal Predictions and False Percepts</h3> <p>During the internal mode, the brain exploits <strong>predictive templates</strong> for perceptual decision-making. Predictive templates that don’t align with reality can lead to misperceptions or <strong>false alarms</strong> — a hallmark of hallucinations. GLM-HMMs indicate that these templates are amplified in individuals with psychosis-proneness.</p> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>We used an integrated approach across:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Behavior experiments</strong> to induce competition between internal and external interpretations.</li> <li><strong>GLM-HMM</strong> models to infer latent mode dynamics from behavior.</li> <li><strong>S-ketamine experiments</strong> to simulate NMDA receptor hypofunction.</li> <li><strong>Clinical comparisons</strong> between schizophrenia patients and healthy controls.</li> </ul> <h2 id="implications">Implications</h2> <p>Our findings suggest that the <strong>explore-exploit balance</strong> is a core computational principle of perception — and a potential <strong>biomarker</strong> for psychiatric disorders like schizophrenia. Stabilizing these dynamics could form the basis for targeted therapies aimed at restoring cognitive flexibility and adaptive perception in people living with delusions and hallucinations.</p> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <ul> <li>Real-time monitoring of explore-exploit mode dynamics as a diagnostic tool.</li> <li>Closed-loop interventions to support flexible perceptual inference.</li> <li>Expanding the framework to domains like memory recall, planning, and social cognition.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/modes_Basel_2.html">Interactive Presentation: Internal and External Modes</a></li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Yuki Murai, and David Whitney. “Dynamic Predictive Templates in Perception.” <em>Current Biology</em> 34, no. 18 (September 23, 2024): 4301–4306.e2. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2024.07.087</li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Marcus Rothkirch, Deniz Yilmaz, Merve Fritsch, Lena Esther Ptasczynski, Katrin Reichenbach, Lukas Rödiger, Philip Corlett, and Philipp Sterzer. “N-Methyl-d-Aspartate Receptor Hypofunction Causes Recurrent and Transient Failures of Perceptual Inference.” <em>Brain</em>, January 16, 2025, awaf011. https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awaf011</li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Heiner Stuke, Kai Standvoss, and Philipp Sterzer. “Sensory Processing in Humans and Mice Fluctuates between External and Internal Modes.” <em>PLOS Biology</em> 21, no. 12 (August 12, 2023): e3002410. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002410</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Veith Weilnhammer</name></author><category term="explore-exploit"/><category term="perception"/><category term="cognition"/><category term="hallucinations"/><category term="ketamine"/><category term="GLM-HMM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Perception alternates between external and internal modes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality?</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality?"/><published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Have you ever wondered how your brain makes sense of the world around you? Sensory information is often noisy, incomplete, and ambiguous. Yet, our brains usually construct a coherent experience of reality. My research investigates how specific brain regions — particularly the <strong>inferior frontal cortex (IFC)</strong> and the <strong>anterior insula</strong> — help resolve ambiguity in perception and beyond.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <h3 id="1-the-ifc-resolves-perceptual-ambiguity">1. The IFC Resolves Perceptual Ambiguity</h3> <p>Our experiments show that the IFC plays a crucial role in managing conflicting sensory signals. When we temporarily disrupted IFC activity using Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS), participants experienced slower perceptual shifts in tasks where visual stimuli could be interpreted in multiple ways. This finding suggests the IFC is actively involved in updating our conscious perception when faced with ambiguity.</p> <h3 id="2-the-insula-detects-unexpected-changes">2. The Insula Detects Unexpected Changes</h3> <p>Another key region, the anterior insula, along with the IFC, responds strongly to unexpected changes in both spatial and temporal contexts. These findings indicate that the insula helps detect moments when our predictions about the world fail, prompting the brain to adjust and update its expectations.</p> <h3 id="3-damage-to-ifc-reduces-perceptual-flexibility">3. Damage to IFC Reduces Perceptual Flexibility</h3> <p>In individuals who suffered strokes affecting the IFC, we found a significant reduction in their ability to spontaneously shift perceptions during ambiguous visual tasks. This supports the idea that a healthy IFC is essential for maintaining the flexibility in perception, ensuring our conscious experience remains dynamic and responsive.</p> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>To arrive at these conclusions, we used a diverse set of approaches:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Behavioral experiments</strong> using ambiguous visual stimuli.</li> <li><strong>Functional MRI (fMRI)</strong> to observe brain activity related to prediction errors.</li> <li><strong>Brain stimulation (TMS)</strong> to demonstrate causal relationships between IFC activity and perceptual updating.</li> <li><strong>Lesion studies</strong> in stroke patients with localized damage to IFC.</li> </ul> <h2 id="implications">Implications</h2> <p>Our findings provide valuable insights into how higher-order brain regions shape our perception. This research supports theories of predictive processing, which suggest that the brain continuously generates and updates internal predictions to interpret sensory information. The IFC, identified as a critical node in this network, could also be a promising target for therapeutic strategies aimed at addressing perceptual and cognitive disorders involving rigid or unstable perceptions.</p> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>Looking ahead, we plan to:</p> <ul> <li>Develop real-time methods to track prediction errors and perceptual updates.</li> <li>Explore targeted brain stimulation techniques to enhance or restore perceptual flexibility.</li> <li>Extend our research framework to other cognitive functions such as memory recall and belief updating.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/CCN.html">Interactive Presentation: Is the IFC part of the NCC?</a></li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Merve Fritsch, Meera Chikermane, Anna-Lena Eckert, Katharina Kanthak, Heiner Stuke, Jakob Kaminski, and Philipp Sterzer. “An Active Role of Inferior Frontal Cortex in Conscious Experience.” <em>Current Biology</em> 31, no. 13 (July 12, 2021): 2868–2880.e8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.043</li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Karin Ludwig, Guido Hesselmann, and Philipp Sterzer. “Frontoparietal Cortex Mediates Perceptual Transitions in Bistable Perception.” <em>The Journal of Neuroscience</em> 33, no. 40 (October 2, 2013): 16009–15. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1418-13.2013</li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Heiner Stuke, Guido Hesselmann, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. “A Predictive Coding Account of Bistable Perception – A Model-Based fMRI Study.” <em>PLOS Computational Biology</em> 13, no. 5 (May 15, 2017): e1005536. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005536</li> <li>Weilnhammer, Veith, Heiner Stuke, Philipp Sterzer, and Katharina Schmack. “The Neural Correlates of Hierarchical Predictions for Perceptual Decisions.” <em>The Journal of Neuroscience</em> 38, no. 21 (May 23, 2018): 5008–21. https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2901-17.2018</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Veith Weilnhammer</name></author><category term="consciousness"/><category term="perception"/><category term="inference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The role of the inferior frontal cortex in resolving sensory ambiguity.]]></summary></entry></feed>