<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-16T19:00:09+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How does perception balance new information with prior knowledge?</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does perception balance new information with prior knowledge?"/><published>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Perception requires the brain to continually balance incoming sensory signals with internal predictions. Our research explores how perception dynamically fluctuates between two distinct modes: an <strong>external mode</strong>, dominated by immediate sensory inputs, and an <strong>internal mode</strong>, shaped by prior expectations and experiences. These perceptual modes are particularly relevant in understanding conditions like schizophrenia, where disruptions in sensory integration can lead to psychosis and hallucinations.</p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>Predictive processing theories propose that psychosis results from impaired integration between sensory information and internal predictive models. Central to this integration is the <strong>N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDAR)</strong>, a receptor consistently implicated in schizophrenia. We investigated whether perceptual symptoms in psychosis might emerge from dynamic shifts between external and internal perceptual modes, driven by disruptions in NMDAR functioning.</p> <h2 id="key-findings-across-studies">Key Findings Across Studies</h2> <h3 id="1-human-and-animal-perception-cycles-between-internal-and-external-modes-plos-biology-weilnhammer-et-al-2023">1. Human and animal perception cycles between internal and external modes (PLOS Biology, Weilnhammer et al., 2023)</h3> <p>Using large-scale datasets from humans and mice, we found systematic fluctuations in perception between external mode (high sensory accuracy, minimal bias) and internal mode (strong reliance on prior experiences, high bias). Computational models (GLM-HMMs) revealed these fluctuations are not random, but reflect a structured mechanism that balances sensory novelty and perceptual stability.</p> <h3 id="2-predictive-templates-drive-false-perceptions-current-biology-weilnhammer-et-al-2024">2. Predictive templates drive false perceptions (Current Biology, Weilnhammer et al., 2024)</h3> <p>False alarms—perceiving signals in the absence of actual sensory input—offer insights into hallucinatory experiences. We found that false alarms arise from dynamically fluctuating internal predictions (“predictive templates”) shaped by recent perceptual history. These templates dominate during internal perceptual modes, increasing vulnerability to hallucinations.</p> <h3 id="3-nmdar-dysfunction-disrupts-perceptual-mode-balance-brain-weilnhammer-et-al-2024">3. NMDAR dysfunction disrupts perceptual mode balance (Brain, Weilnhammer et al., 2024)</h3> <p>Pharmacologically induced NMDAR hypofunction (via S-ketamine) and schizophrenia both resulted in prolonged external perceptual modes. This heightened sensory-driven perception causes transient disconnects from stable internal predictive models, providing a neurocomputational explanation for episodic psychotic symptoms.</p> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>Together, our findings illustrate how dynamic shifts between external and internal perceptual modes influence psychotic experiences. An overly dominant external mode leads to unstable sensory interpretations under ambiguous conditions. In turn, this instability shapes maladaptive predictive templates, causing psychotic experiences when internal mode prevails. Understanding these dynamics opens avenues for interventions aimed at stabilizing perception in schizophrenia.</p> <h2 id="approach-and-methodology">Approach and Methodology</h2> <p>We employed a multi-method approach:</p> <ul> <li>Behavioral psychophysics with ambiguous sensory stimuli (structure-from-motion, noise paradigms).</li> <li>Computational modeling (HMM-GLM) to quantify and explain perceptual mode dynamics.</li> <li>Pharmacological studies using S-ketamine to model NMDAR hypofunction.</li> <li>Clinical comparisons between schizophrenia patients and healthy controls.</li> </ul> <h2 id="relevance-and-clinical-implications">Relevance and Clinical Implications</h2> <p>Our work deepens the understanding of perceptual inference deficits underlying psychosis. By clarifying how dynamic perceptual fluctuations relate to NMDAR dysfunction, we identify potential biomarkers for psychosis risk and highlight new targets for therapeutic interventions, such as closed-loop neuromodulation to stabilize perceptual modes.</p> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>Our findings open promising paths forward:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Real-time perceptual tracking:</strong> Developing continuous methods to track perceptual mode shifts for early psychosis detection.</li> <li><strong>Neuromodulation therapies:</strong> Exploring brain stimulation and pharmacological interventions to stabilize perceptual inference and reduce psychotic symptoms.</li> <li><strong>Extension to cognition:</strong> Applying this computational framework to memory, decision-making, and other cognitive functions impaired in psychosis.</li> </ul> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="papers">Papers:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002410">Sensory processing in humans and mice</a> <em>(PLOS Biology, open access)</em></li> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2024.07.087">Dynamic predictive templates in perception</a> <em>(Current Biology, open access)</em></li> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awaf011">NMDAR hypofunction and perceptual inference</a> <em>(Brain, open access)</em></li> </ul> <h3 id="presentations">Presentations:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/modes_Basel_2.html">Presentation: External and Internal Modes in Perception</a></li> </ul> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="schizophrenia"/><category term="psychosis"/><category term="hallucinations"/><category term="ketamine"/><category term="HMM-GLM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[External and internal modes of perceptual inference.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Psychotherapie</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Psychotherapie"/><published>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapie</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapie/"><![CDATA[<p>Mein Anliegen ist es, evidenzbasierte psychische Gesundheitsversorgung für alle zugänglich zu machen. Ich biete Online-Psychotherapie, Coaching, Beratung und Unterstützung für Menschen mit psychischen Belastungen an.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="über-mich">Über mich</h2> <p>Ich bin Facharzt für Psychiatrie und Psychotherapie. Meine klinische Ausbildung habe ich an der Charité in Berlin abgeschlossen. Am Zentrum für Psychotherapie der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin habe ich mich in <strong>kognitiver Verhaltenstherapie</strong> und <strong>systemischer Psychotherapie</strong> weitergebildet. Zu meinen zentralen Prinzipien und Methoden zählen:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Kognitive Verhaltenstherapie (KVT)</strong>: Wissenschaftlich fundierte Strategien, um ungesunde Denkmuster und Verhaltensweisen zu verändern, Stress zu bewältigen und hilfreichere Strategien zu entwickeln.</li> <li><strong>Achtsamkeits- und Akzeptanzverfahren</strong>: Förderung von Selbstwahrnehmung, Resilienz und Mitgefühl sich selbst gegenüber.</li> <li><strong>Systemische Therapie</strong>: Einbezug familiärer, sozialer und beruflicher Kontexte in die Therapie.</li> <li><strong>Open Dialogue</strong>: Ein kooperativer Ansatz, der auf transparente Kommunikation und gemeinschaftliche Entscheidungsprozesse setzt, insbesondere in Krisensituationen.</li> </ul> <p>Ich begeistere mich für digitale Technologien, um psychische Gesundheit besser zu verstehen, vorherzusagen und zu verbessern. Weitere Informationen zu meiner wissenschaftlichen und klinischen Tätigkeit finden Sie in meinem <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/pdf/CV_Weilnhammer.pdf">Lebenslauf</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="leistungsangebot">Leistungsangebot</h2> <p>Wenn Sie eine Lebenskrise, stressbedingte Probleme oder tiefer gehende psychische Herausforderungen haben, kann <strong>Online-Psychotherapie</strong> eine flexible und effektive Lösung darstellen. Ich biete vertrauliche Sitzungen über <strong>sichere Videogespräche</strong> auf deutsch und englisch an, sodass Sie Unterstützung von Ihrem gewünschten Ort aus erhalten können.</p> <p>Neben der Einzeltherapie biete ich auch:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Gruppentherapie</strong>: Ein geschütztes, moderiertes Umfeld, in dem Klient*innen voneinander lernen und gemeinsam neue Bewältigungsstrategien entwickeln können.</li> <li><strong>Coaching &amp; Beratung</strong>: Individuelle Begleitung bei persönlicher Weiterentwicklung, beruflichen Herausforderungen oder Veränderungsprozessen.</li> </ul> <p>Mein Ziel ist es, Sie dort abzuholen, wo Sie gerade stehen, und Ihnen die nötigen Ressourcen und Unterstützung bereitzustellen. Gerne können wir besprechen, ob Einzeltherapie, Gruppentherapie oder Coaching am besten zu Ihrer Situation passt. Die Verfügbarkeit von Gruppenangeboten und Coaching-Plätzen variiert; kontaktieren Sie mich bitte, um mehr über freie Kapazitäten und Terminoptionen zu erfahren.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="ablauf-der-therapie">Ablauf der Therapie</h2> <p>In den ersten Sitzungen werden wir:</p> <ul> <li>Ihre aktuellen Anliegen und persönlichen Ziele erörtern.</li> <li>Relevante Hintergrundinformationen (z. B. medizinische oder psychologische Vorgeschichte) besprechen.</li> <li>Gemeinsam einen Behandlungsplan erstellen, der Ihren Bedürfnissen entspricht und z. B. eine oder zwei Siztungen pro Woche umfassen kann.</li> </ul> <p>Jede Sitzung dauert in der Regel <strong>50 Minuten</strong> und kann folgende Inhalte umfassen:</p> <ul> <li>Reflexion aktueller Erfahrungen oder Veränderungen in Stimmung, Denken und Verhalten</li> <li>Identifikation und Bearbeitung belastender oder negativer Denkmuster</li> <li>Einübung neuer Bewältigungsstrategien</li> <li>Festlegung von Zielen und „Hausaufgaben“ für den Zeitraum zwischen den Sitzungen</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="kosten--versicherung">Kosten &amp; Versicherung</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Selbstzahlende</strong>: Bitte kontaktieren Sie mich direkt für Informationen zu den Sitzungsgebühren oder möglichen Ermäßigungen.</li> <li><strong>Versicherungsleistungen</strong>: Viele Krankenversicherungen übernehmen einen Teil oder sogar die vollständigen Kosten für Psychotherapie. Informieren Sie sich bei Ihrer Versicherung über Ihren individuellen Tarif und Leistungsumfang.</li> </ul> <p>Sollten finanzielle Aspekte eine Hürde darstellen, zögern Sie nicht, mich anzusprechen — mein Anliegen ist es, eine möglichst barrierearme Versorgung zu ermöglichen.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="kontakt--terminvereinbarung">Kontakt &amp; Terminvereinbarung</h2> <p>Wenn Sie einen Termin vereinbaren oder mehr Informationen erhalten möchten, schreiben Sie mir bitte eine E-Mail an: <a href="mailto:veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com">veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com</a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="haftungsausschluss">Haftungsausschluss</h2> <p>Diese Website dient ausschließlich Informationszwecken und ersetzt keine professionelle medizinische Beratung, Diagnose oder Behandlung. Bei akuten Krisen oder Notfällen wenden Sie sich bitte an den zuständigen Notdienst in Ihrer Region.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pages"/><category term="psychotherapy"/><category term="mental-health"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Erfahren Sie mehr über meinen psychotherapeutischen Ansatz und wie Sie einen Termin vereinbaren können.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online psychotherapy</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online psychotherapy"/><published>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/psychotherapy/"><![CDATA[<p>My mission is to make evidence-based mental healthcare accessible to everyone. I offer online psychotherapy, coaching, counseling, and support for people experiencing mental health challenges.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="about-me">About Me</h2> <p>I am a board-certified psychiatrist and psychotherapist. I completed my clinical training at the Charité in Berlin. I trained in <strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</strong> and <strong>Systemic Psychotherapy</strong> at the Center for Psychotherapy, Humboldt University of Berlin. Here are some key principles and methods I draw upon:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</strong>: Evidence-based strategies to reframe unhelpful patterns of thought and behavior, manage stress, and develop more adaptive coping skills.</li> <li><strong>Mindfulness and Acceptance Techniques</strong>: Develop awareness, resilience, and compassion for oneself.</li> <li><strong>Systemic Therapy</strong>: Considers your concerns within the broader context of family, social, and professional systems.</li> <li><strong>Open Dialogue</strong>: A collaborative approach focusing on transparent communication and a shared decision-making process, especially helpful in crisis situations.</li> </ul> <p>I am passionate about digital technologies to better understand, predict, and improve mental health. If you would like more details about my work as a scientist and clinician, you can find my <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/pdf/CV_Weilnhammer.pdf">CV here</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="range-of-services">Range of Services</h2> <p>If you’re experiencing a life crisis, stress-related concerns, or deeper mental health issues, <strong>online psychotherapy</strong> can be a flexible and effective solution. I provide confidential sessions via <strong>secure video calls</strong> in german and english, enabling you to receive support from the comfort of your own space.</p> <p>In addition to one-on-one therapy, I also offer:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Group Therapy</strong>: A safe, moderated space where clients can learn from each other’s experiences and practice new skills in a supportive environment.</li> <li><strong>Coaching &amp; Counseling</strong>: Tailored guidance for personal development, career challenges, or transitional life phases.</li> </ul> <p>My goal is to meet you where you are and ensure you have the resources and support you need. Please feel free to reach out to discuss which format (individual, group, or coaching) might best suit your situation. Availability for group therapy and coaching may vary, so contact me to learn more about open slots and scheduling options.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-to-expect-in-therapy">What to Expect in Therapy</h2> <p>During the first sessions, we will:</p> <ul> <li>Discuss your current concerns and personal goals.</li> <li>Explore relevant background information (e.g., medical and psychological history).</li> <li>Co-create a treatment plan that best fits your needs, which can include weekly or bi-weekly sessions.</li> </ul> <p>Each session typically runs <strong>50 minutes</strong> and may involve:</p> <ul> <li>Discussing recent experiences or changes in mood or perspective</li> <li>Identifying and challenging negative thought patterns or core beliefs</li> <li>Practicing new coping strategies</li> <li>Setting goals and homework to use between sessions</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="fees--insurance">Fees &amp; Insurance</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Self-Paying Clients</strong>: Please contact me directly for information about session fees or potential sliding-scale arrangements.</li> <li><strong>Insurance Coverage</strong>: Many health insurance providers offer partial or full reimbursement for therapy costs. Kindly check with your insurer about your specific plan and benefits.</li> </ul> <p>If cost is a concern, feel free to reach out — I’m committed to helping make care as accessible as possible.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact--booking">Contact &amp; Booking</h2> <p>To schedule an appointment or request more information, please send me an email: <a href="mailto:veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com">veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com</a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2> <p>This website is for informational purposes only. It is not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. If you need immediate help or are experiencing a crisis, please contact a mental health care provider or the emergency services in your area.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pages"/><category term="psychotherapy"/><category term="mental-health"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn more about my approach to psychotherapy, and how to book a session.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality, and how do they fail in psychosis?</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality, and how do they fail in psychosis?"/><published>2024-03-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Conscious perception is a complex cognitive process involving continuous integration and interpretation of ambiguous sensory inputs. Our work examines how frontoparietal brain regions — particularly the <strong>inferior frontal cortex (IFC)</strong> and <strong>anterior insula</strong> — detect and resolve perceptual ambiguities. Using human neuroimaging, computational modeling, clinical lesion studies, and non-invasive brain stimulation, we have explored how these regions dynamically manage sensory conflicts to maintain coherent and stable conscious experience.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>Perception inherently involves uncertainty, requiring the brain to constantly resolve ambiguous inputs. Bistable perception exemplifies this process, as observers experience spontaneous alternations between two mutually exclusive perceptual states despite unchanging sensory input.</p> <p>Predictive processing theories propose that perception involves continuous interaction between incoming sensory signals and internal predictive models. When predictions conflict with sensory input, prediction errors are thought to occur and lead up to changes in perception. Our research examines the computational and neural mechanisms underlying this dynamic resolution of perceptual conflicts, focusing on the role of frontoparietal regions — primarily the inferior frontal cortex and anterior insula.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="key-findings-across-studies">Key Findings Across Studies</h2> <h3 id="1-inferior-frontal-cortex-resolves-perceptual-ambiguities-current-biology-weilnhammer-et-al-2021">1. Inferior Frontal Cortex resolves perceptual ambiguities (Current Biology, Weilnhammer et al., 2021)</h3> <p>Our combined fMRI and transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) studies showed that the inferior frontal cortex actively detects perceptual conflicts in bistable perception tasks. Crucially, transient disruption of IFC activity through TMS slowed perceptual updates, demonstrating IFC’s causal role in resolving sensory ambiguity and shaping conscious perception.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="2-anterior-insula-detects-generalized-perceptual-conflicts-biorxiv-reichenbach-et-al-2024">2. Anterior Insula detects generalized perceptual conflicts (bioRxiv, Reichenbach et al., 2024)</h3> <p>We investigated whether frontoparietal conflict detection generalizes beyond temporal context (past perceptual experiences) to include spatial context (surrounding perceptual environment). We found that perceptual conflicts that conflicts with spatial and temporal contexts activated common neural substrates, prominently the bilateral anterior insula and right inferior frontal cortex. This suggests a generalized predictive-processing mechanism within frontoparietal regions for resolving various forms of perceptual ambiguity.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="3-structural-lesions-confirm-ifcs-role-in-conscious-perception-biorxiv-fritsch-et-al-2024">3. Structural lesions confirm IFC’s role in conscious perception (bioRxiv, Fritsch et al., 2024)</h3> <p>Extending our approach to structural lesions, we examined patients with ischemic strokes affecting the IFC. Compared to stroke patients without IFC lesions, those with IFC lesions showed fewer spontaneous perceptual switches when viewing ambiguous visual stimuli. This finding strongly reinforces the causal role of IFC in mediating dynamic perceptual updates and conscious visual experience.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>Together, these studies highlight a cohesive neurocomputational framework for conscious perception, emphasizing the active role of frontoparietal regions — especially the inferior frontal cortex and anterior insula — in detecting and resolving sensory ambiguity. The inferior frontal cortex specifically emerges as critical for transforming ambiguous sensory information into stable conscious experiences.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="approach-and-methodology">Approach and Methodology</h2> <p>We employed a multidisciplinary methodology integrating:</p> <ul> <li>Behavioral psychophysics and bistable perception paradigms to measure perceptual states and transitions in human participants.</li> <li>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) combined with computational modeling to identify neural correlates of perceptual conflict.</li> <li>Clinical lesion studies comparing patients with selective IFC damage against control patients, assessing the causal impact of IFC dysfunction on perception.</li> <li>Non-invasive neuromodulation techniques (TMS) to establish causal links between IFC activity and perceptual conflict resolution mechanisms.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="relevance-and-clinical-implications">Relevance and Clinical Implications</h2> <p>Our findings refine the predictive processing framework by clarifying the precise neurocomputational roles of frontal and insular regions in perceptual inference. By highlighting IFC’s role in resolving perceptual conflicts, our research contributes to a deeper understanding of the neural bases of consciousness and has significant clinical relevance. Frontoparietal mechanisms for conflict resolution could represent novel biomarkers or therapeutic targets in disorders characterized by perceptual instability, such as schizophrenia, offering opportunities for innovative neuromodulatory interventions to stabilize conscious perception.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>Building on these insights, future research will explore:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Real-time neural monitoring:</strong> Developing methods to continuously track perceptual mode fluctuations and IFC activation, aiming at predicting and managing psychotic episodes.</li> <li><strong>Broader cognitive applications:</strong> Extending the investigation to related cognitive domains, such as memory and decision-making, to comprehensively map the influence of IFC-mediated conflict resolution across various cognitive processes.</li> <li><strong>Clinical neuromodulation:</strong> Testing closed-loop neuromodulation approaches targeting IFC and related frontoparietal regions to therapeutically stabilize disrupted perception in clinical populations.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="publications">Publications:</h3> <ul> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.043">Inferior frontal cortex and perceptual conflict (Current Biology, 2021)</a></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.05.29.595872">Anterior insula and prediction errors (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.24.609496">IFC lesions and conscious perception (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="presentations">Presentations:</h3> <ul> <li>🎞️ <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/CCN.html">Project presentation: Is the IFC part of the NCC?</a></li> </ul> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="consciousness"/><category term="perception"/><category term="inference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The role of frontoparietal networks in resolving sensory ambiguity]]></summary></entry></feed>