<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-13T12:12:52+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">External and internal modes of perception</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/external_internal_perception/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="External and internal modes of perception"/><published>2024-06-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/external_internal_perception</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/external_internal_perception/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How does perception balance new infomration with prior knowledge?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Psychotherapy &amp;amp; Mental Health Services</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/psychotherapy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychotherapy &amp;amp; Mental Health Services"/><published>2024-01-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/psychotherapy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2024/psychotherapy/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="welcome-to-my-psychotherapy-practice">Welcome to My Psychotherapy Practice</h1> <p>Hello and thank you for visiting my website! I’m a <strong>psychiatrist</strong>, <strong>psychotherapist</strong>, and <strong>neuroscientist</strong>, offering a blend of evidence-based treatments in a supportive setting. My goal is to help you navigate life’s challenges, develop resilience, and achieve genuine well-being.</p> <p>This site contains information about my approach, credentials, and services. Please feel free to reach out if you have any questions or if you would like to schedule a session.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="my-therapeutic-approach">My Therapeutic Approach</h2> <p>I believe in a <strong>holistic approach</strong> to mental health, combining multiple modalities to best serve each client. Here are some key principles and methods I draw upon:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</strong>: Work on practical strategies to reframe unhelpful thinking patterns.</li> <li><strong>Systemic Psychotherapy</strong>: Understand the interplay between individual behaviors and wider social or family dynamics.</li> <li><strong>Mindfulness and Acceptance Techniques</strong>: Develop awareness, resilience, and compassion for oneself.</li> <li><strong>Evidence-Based Medicine</strong>: Use research-backed interventions that align with modern psychiatric and neuroscientific findings.</li> </ul> <p>I’ve previously worked in inpatient and outpatient settings, and have a special interest in <strong>schizophrenia</strong>, <strong>mood disorders</strong>, and <strong>stress-related conditions</strong>. I also offer <strong>ketamine- and TMS-assisted treatments</strong> under specific circumstances and settings, as well as digital mental health tools to monitor and improve mental well-being.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="about-me">About Me</h2> <p>I am a board-certified <strong>psychiatrist</strong> and <strong>psychotherapist</strong>, with a background in <strong>neuroscience</strong>. My recent focus includes developing digital technologies to better understand, predict, and improve mental health. I completed my medical studies and subsequent doctoral degree at Charité in Berlin, Germany, with additional training at the University of California, Berkeley.</p> <p><strong>Selected Highlights</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>Board-certified in Psychiatry &amp; Psychotherapy (2023)</li> <li>Habilitation degree in Experimental Psychiatry (2023)</li> <li>Visiting scholar at the Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute, UC Berkeley</li> <li>Research areas include visual perception, neural correlates of consciousness, and neurobiology of psychosis</li> <li>Previous clinician scientist fellowship at the Berlin Institute of Health</li> </ul> <p>If you would like more details about my research background or publications, you can check my <a href="#">CV here</a> or browse my GitHub and Google Scholar profiles for up-to-date listings.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-to-expect-in-therapy">What to Expect in Therapy</h2> <p>During the first session, we will:</p> <ol> <li>Discuss your current concerns and personal goals.</li> <li>Explore relevant background information (e.g., medical and psychological history).</li> <li>Co-create a treatment plan that best fits your needs, which can include weekly or bi-weekly sessions.</li> </ol> <h3 id="session-structure">Session Structure</h3> <p>Each session typically runs <strong>50 minutes</strong> and may involve:</p> <ul> <li>Discussing recent experiences or changes in mood or perspective</li> <li>Identifying and challenging negative thought patterns or core beliefs</li> <li>Practicing new coping strategies</li> <li>Setting goals and homework to use between sessions</li> </ul> <h3 id="confidentiality">Confidentiality</h3> <p>Your privacy is paramount. All sessions are confidential within the limits of professional ethical standards and legal requirements.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="fees--insurance">Fees &amp; Insurance</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Self-Paying Clients</strong>: Standard session fees range from $XX to $YY, based on income or sliding-scale availability.</li> <li><strong>Insurance</strong>: Some health insurance plans cover part or all of therapy costs. Please contact your insurer for details.</li> </ul> <p>If cost is a barrier, feel free to discuss options with me—my priority is accessible care.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact--booking">Contact &amp; Booking</h2> <p><strong>Phone</strong>: <a href="tel:+13413339788">+1 341 333 9788</a><br/> <strong>Email</strong>: <a href="mailto:veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com">veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com</a><br/> <strong>Address</strong>: University of California, Berkeley (Helen Wills Neuroscience Institute)</p> <p>To schedule an appointment or request more information, please send me an email or give me a call. I offer both <strong>in-person</strong> and <strong>telehealth sessions</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="additional-resources">Additional Resources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://github.com/veithweilnhammer">My GitHub</a> – for research code and other public projects.</li> <li><a href="https://scholar.google.de/citations?user=k_wJmK0AAAAJ">Google Scholar Profile</a> – peer-reviewed publications.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h3> <p>This website is for informational purposes only. It is not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. If you need immediate help or are experiencing a crisis, please contact emergency services in your area.</p> <hr/> <p><em>By combining my clinical training, research background, and personalized therapy approach, I aim to empower you in your healing process. I look forward to the opportunity to work with you.</em></p> <hr/> <p><em>Thank you for visiting my psychotherapy website! If you have any questions or would like to book a session, feel free to get in touch.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pages"/><category term="therapy"/><category term="psychotherapy"/><category term="mental-health"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn more about my psychotherapy approach, background, and how to book a session.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Concepts and models of schizophrenia</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/concepts_schizophrenia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concepts and models of schizophrenia"/><published>2022-04-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/concepts_schizophrenia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/concepts_schizophrenia/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How has the understanding of schizophrenia changed over time?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The neural correlates of consciousness in health and in psychosis</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/NCC_health_psychosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The neural correlates of consciousness in health and in psychosis"/><published>2022-02-01T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/NCC_health_psychosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/2022/NCC_health_psychosis/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality, and how do they fail in psychosis?]]></summary></entry></feed>