<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-16T18:52:40+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dynamic fluctuations between external and internal modes of perception: Neural mechanisms, predictive templates, and implications for psychosis</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dynamic fluctuations between external and internal modes of perception: Neural mechanisms, predictive templates, and implications for psychosis"/><published>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Perception is not simply passive processing of sensory signals; rather, it involves actively integrating incoming sensory information with internal predictions shaped by prior experiences. Our work explores how perception dynamically alternates between two distinct states:</p> <ul> <li><strong>External mode</strong>: Perception is strongly driven by immediate sensory input, enhancing the accurate processing of new information.</li> <li><strong>Internal mode</strong>: Perception is biased toward previous experiences, reflecting internal predictive models rather than external reality.</li> </ul> <p>These perceptual modes have important implications for understanding and treating psychosis, particularly schizophrenia, where perceptual inference frequently goes awry.</p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>Predictive processing theories suggest that psychotic symptoms like hallucinations and delusions emerge from impaired integration of sensory information with internal expectations. OUr research investigates the neural and computational mechanisms underlying these failures of perceptual inference, particularly focusing on the role of <strong>N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDAR)</strong> hypofunction—a key neural abnormality in schizophrenia.</p> <p>By combining human psychophysics, computational modeling, and pharmacological interventions, we’ve explored how transient, dynamic shifts between external and internal perceptual modes might explain the episodic and fluctuating nature of psychotic symptoms.</p> <h2 id="key-findings-across-studies">Key Findings Across Studies</h2> <h3 id="1-perception-alternates-between-external-and-internal-modes-plos-biology">1. Perception alternates between external and internal modes (PLOS Biology)</h3> <ul> <li>Using large-scale behavioral datasets from humans and mice, we found that perception systematically cycles between: <ul> <li><strong>External mode</strong> (high accuracy, low serial dependence)</li> <li><strong>Internal mode</strong> (low accuracy, strong serial dependence)</li> </ul> </li> <li>These mode fluctuations appear structured rather than random, suggesting a fundamental computational strategy to balance novelty detection (external mode) and stability through predictive modeling (internal mode).</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-dynamic-predictive-templates-drive-perceptual-false-alarms-current-biology">2. Dynamic predictive templates drive perceptual false alarms (Current Biology)</h3> <ul> <li>False alarms (perceiving signals when none exist) serve as a powerful model for understanding hallucinations.</li> <li>These false alarms are not random but driven by “predictive templates,” internal predictions about sensory input shaped by recent experiences.</li> <li>Using Hidden Markov Models (HMMs), we revealed that these templates fluctuate dynamically, with false alarms becoming more frequent and strongly biased toward past experiences during internal modes.</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-nmdar-hypofunction-causes-recurrent-perceptual-inference-failures-brain">3. NMDAR hypofunction causes recurrent perceptual inference failures (Brain)</h3> <ul> <li>Pharmacological induction of NMDAR hypofunction using S-ketamine in healthy participants mimicked key perceptual disruptions observed in schizophrenia.</li> <li>Both S-ketamine administration and schizophrenia resulted in prolonged external mode, causing transient dissociations from internal predictive models.</li> <li>These recurring shifts toward external mode provide a mechanistic explanation for episodic psychotic experiences, suggesting that NMDAR dysfunction causes a shift in the natural oscillation between perceptual modes.</li> </ul> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>The dynamic interplay between external and internal modes is crucial for understanding perceptual inference and psychosis. In the external mode, perception is overly reliant on immediate sensory signals, leading to erratic inferences when sensory information is ambiguous or noisy. Over time, this can result in the formation of maladaptive internal knowledge structures. Consequently, when the system switches into the internal mode, these maladaptive predictions dominate perception, potentially giving rise to psychotic experiences such as hallucinations and delusions. Understanding and potentially stabilizing these perceptual mode fluctuations thus represents a promising avenue for novel therapeutic interventions in schizophrenia and related psychotic disorders.</p> <h2 id="approach-and-methodology">Approach and Methodology</h2> <p>Across these studies, we used:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Behavioral psychophysics</strong> with ambiguous sensory stimuli (structure-from-motion, signal-in-noise paradigms) to quantify perceptual mode shifts.</li> <li><strong>Computational modeling</strong> using General Linear Models combined with Hidden Markov Models (GLM-HMMs) to capture dynamic fluctuations in perceptual inference.</li> <li><strong>Pharmacological interventions</strong> (S-ketamine administration) and case-control clinical studies (schizophrenia patients vs. controls) to causally link perceptual dynamics to neural mechanisms.</li> </ul> <h2 id="relevance-and-clinical-implications">Relevance and Clinical Implications</h2> <p>Our work advances predictive processing accounts of psychosis by highlighting dynamic fluctuations between perceptual modes as a core computational mechanism underlying transient psychotic symptoms:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Neurocomputational models:</strong> Clarifies how NMDAR hypofunction disrupt perceptual inference mechanisms.</li> <li><strong>Clinical translation:</strong> Identifies potential biomarkers (dynamic mode fluctuations) for psychosis monitoring and suggests novel targets for therapeutic intervention, possibly through real-time neuromodulation to stabilize mode transitions.</li> <li><strong>Theoretical integration:</strong> Strengthens the link between basic perceptual neuroscience and clinical psychiatry, providing a mechanistic framework for understanding why hallucinations and other psychotic symptoms are transient and episodic rather than constant.</li> </ul> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>Several promising research avenues emerge from these findings:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Real-time mode tracking:</strong> Developing methods to continuously monitor external-internal perceptual mode shifts as early indicators of psychotic episodes.</li> <li><strong>Closed-loop neuromodulation:</strong> Investigating interventions (e.g., brain stimulation, pharmacological adjustments) that might stabilize perceptual inference, reducing symptom severity.</li> <li><strong>Broader cognitive domains:</strong> Extending this computational approach to memory, decision-making, and other cognitive functions to understand their contributions to psychotic disorders comprehensively.</li> </ul> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="papers-and-presentations">Papers and Presentations:</h3> <ul> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/brain/awaf011">NMDAR hypofunction and perceptual inference</a> <em>(open access)</em></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.3002410">Sensory processing in humans and mice</a> <em>(open access)</em></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2024.07.087">Dynamic predictive templates in perception</a> <em>(open access)</em></li> </ul> <h3 id="talks-and-slides">Talks and Slides:</h3> <ul> <li> <h2 id="️-presentation-external-and-internal-modes-in-perception">🎞️ <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/modes_Basel_2.html">Presentation: External and Internal Modes in Perception</a></h2> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="schizophrenia"/><category term="psychosis"/><category term="halluciantions"/><category term="ketamine"/><category term="HMM-GLM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How does perception balance new infomration with prior knowledge?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neural and computational mechanisms of conscious perception: The role of frontoparietal networks in resolving sensory ambiguity</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neural and computational mechanisms of conscious perception: The role of frontoparietal networks in resolving sensory ambiguity"/><published>2024-03-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Conscious perception is a complex cognitive process involving continuous integration and interpretation of ambiguous sensory inputs. Our work examines how frontoparietal brain regions — particularly the <strong>inferior frontal cortex (IFC)</strong> and <strong>anterior insula</strong> — detect and resolve perceptual ambiguities. Using human neuroimaging, computational modeling, clinical lesion studies, and non-invasive brain stimulation, we have explored how these regions dynamically manage sensory conflicts to maintain coherent and stable conscious experience.</p> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>Perception inherently involves uncertainty, requiring the brain to constantly resolve ambiguous inputs. Bistable perception exemplifies this process, as observers experience spontaneous alternations between two mutually exclusive perceptual states despite unchanging sensory input.</p> <p>Predictive processing theories propose that perception involves continuous interaction between incoming sensory signals and internal predictive models. When predictions conflict with sensory input, prediction errors are thought to occur and lead up to changes in perception. Our research examines the computational and neural mechanisms underlying this dynamic resolution of perceptual conflicts, focusing on the role of frontoparietal regions — primarily the inferior frontal cortex and anterior insula.</p> <h2 id="key-findings-across-studies">Key Findings Across Studies</h2> <h3 id="1-inferior-frontal-cortex-resolves-perceptual-ambiguities-current-biology-weilnhammer-et-al-2021">1. Inferior Frontal Cortex resolves perceptual ambiguities (Current Biology, Weilnhammer et al., 2021)</h3> <p>Our combined fMRI and transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) studies showed that the inferior frontal cortex actively detects perceptual conflicts in bistable perception tasks. Crucially, transient disruption of IFC activity through TMS slowed perceptual updates, demonstrating IFC’s causal role in resolving sensory ambiguity and shaping conscious perception.</p> <h3 id="2-anterior-insula-detects-generalized-perceptual-conflicts-biorxiv-reichenbach-et-al-2024">2. Anterior Insula detects generalized perceptual conflicts (bioRxiv, Reichenbach et al., 2024)</h3> <p>We investigated whether frontoparietal conflict detection generalizes beyond temporal context (past perceptual experiences) to include spatial context (surrounding perceptual environment). We found that perceptual conflicts that conflicts with spatial and temporal contexts activated common neural substrates, prominently the bilateral anterior insula and right inferior frontal cortex. This suggests a generalized predictive-processing mechanism within frontoparietal regions for resolving various forms of perceptual ambiguity.</p> <h3 id="3-structural-lesions-confirm-ifcs-role-in-conscious-perception-biorxiv-fritsch-et-al-2024">3. Structural lesions confirm IFC’s role in conscious perception (bioRxiv, Fritsch et al., 2024)</h3> <p>Extending our approach to structural lesions, we examined patients with ischemic strokes affecting the IFC. Compared to stroke patients without IFC lesions, those with IFC lesions showed fewer spontaneous perceptual switches when viewing ambiguous visual stimuli. This finding strongly reinforces the causal role of IFC in mediating dynamic perceptual updates and conscious visual experience.</p> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>Together, these studies highlight a cohesive neurocomputational framework for conscious perception, emphasizing the active role of frontoparietal regions — especially the inferior frontal cortex and anterior insula — in detecting and resolving sensory ambiguity. The inferior frontal cortex specifically emerges as critical for transforming ambiguous sensory information into stable conscious experiences.</p> <h2 id="approach-and-methodology">Approach and Methodology</h2> <p>We employed a multidisciplinary methodology integrating:</p> <ul> <li>Behavioral psychophysics and bistable perception paradigms to measure perceptual states and transitions in human participants.</li> <li>Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) combined with computational modeling to identify neural correlates of perceptual conflict.</li> <li>Clinical lesion studies comparing patients with selective IFC damage against control patients, assessing the causal impact of IFC dysfunction on perception.</li> <li>Non-invasive neuromodulation techniques (TMS) to establish causal links between IFC activity and perceptual conflict resolution mechanisms.</li> </ul> <h2 id="relevance-and-clinical-implications">Relevance and Clinical Implications</h2> <p>Our findings refine the predictive processing framework by clarifying the precise neurocomputational roles of frontal and insular regions in perceptual inference. By highlighting IFC’s role in resolving perceptual conflicts, our research contributes to a deeper understanding of the neural bases of consciousness and has significant clinical relevance. Frontoparietal mechanisms for conflict resolution could represent novel biomarkers or therapeutic targets in disorders characterized by perceptual instability, such as schizophrenia, offering opportunities for innovative neuromodulatory interventions to stabilize conscious perception.</p> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>Building on these insights, future research will explore:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Real-time neural monitoring:</strong> Developing methods to continuously track perceptual mode fluctuations and IFC activation, aiming at predicting and managing psychotic episodes.</li> <li><strong>Broader cognitive applications:</strong> Extending the investigation to related cognitive domains, such as memory and decision-making, to comprehensively map the influence of IFC-mediated conflict resolution across various cognitive processes.</li> <li><strong>Clinical neuromodulation:</strong> Testing closed-loop neuromodulation approaches targeting IFC and related frontoparietal regions to therapeutically stabilize disrupted perception in clinical populations.</li> </ul> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="papers-and-presentations">Papers and Presentations:</h3> <ul> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.043">Inferior frontal cortex and perceptual conflict (Current Biology, 2021)</a></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.05.29.595872">Anterior insula and prediction errors (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> <li>📄 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.24.609496">IFC lesions and conscious perception (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="presentations">Presentations:</h3> <ul> <li>🎞️ <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/CCN.html">Project presentation: Is the IFC part of the NCC?</a></li> </ul> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="consciousness"/><category term="perception"/><category term="inference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality, and how do they fail in psychosis?]]></summary></entry></feed>