<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-05T19:36:16+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">How does perception balance prior knowledge with new information?</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does perception balance prior knowledge with new information?"/><published>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/external_internal/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Perception actively integrates new sensory information with internal predictions based on prior experiences. Our research explores how the brain dynamically shifts between two perceptual modes: an <strong>external mode</strong> (focused on immediate sensory input) and an <strong>internal mode</strong> (guided by past experiences). These shifts are key to understanding psychotic disorders such as schizophrenia.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <h3 id="1-internal-vs-external-modes">1. Internal vs External Modes</h3> <p>Using large-scale behavioral data, we demonstrated systematic fluctuations in perception between an external mode (high accuracy, minimal reliance on previous experiences) and an internal mode (strongly biased by perceptual history)<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. These fluctuations optimize perception, balancing novelty detection and stability.</p> <h3 id="2-predictive-templates--hallucinations">2. Predictive Templates &amp; Hallucinations</h3> <p>False perceptions (“false alarms”) arise from internal predictions (“predictive templates”), especially during internal mode<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Computational modeling (HMM-GLM) revealed these templates fluctuate dynamically and linked them to the mechanisms underlying hallucinations.</p> <h3 id="3-nmdar-dysfunction--psychosis">3. NMDAR Dysfunction &amp; Psychosis</h3> <p>We showed that pharmacologically-induced NMDAR hypofunction (using S-ketamine) prolongs external mode dominance, causing erratic perceptual inferences. This mirrors key aspects of perceptual disruptions seen in schizophrenia and offers a mechanistic explanation for episodic psychotic symptoms<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>Dynamic interplay between external and internal perceptual modes significantly influences psychosis. Over-reliance on external sensory input can produce unstable perceptions, leading to maladaptive internal predictions. When perception shifts to internal mode, these maladaptive predictions dominate perception and cognition, triggering hallucinations and delusions.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>We combined multiple complementary methodologies:</p> <ul> <li>Behavioral experiments using ambiguous visual stimuli.</li> <li>Computational models (Hidden Markov and General Linear Models, GLM-HMM) to quantify perceptual mode dynamics.</li> <li>Pharmacological experiments with S-ketamine.</li> <li>Clinical studies comparing schizophrenia patients with controls.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="implications">Implications</h2> <p>Clarifying these perceptual dynamics offers important implications for psychiatric care. Dynamic perceptual mode shifts might serve as biomarkers for psychosis, informing novel neuromodulatory treatments targeting NMDAR function and perceptual stability.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <ul> <li>Developing real-time monitoring of perceptual mode shifts as predictive tools for psychosis.</li> <li>Exploring closed-loop neuromodulation techniques to stabilize perceptual inference.</li> <li>Extending our computational framework to related cognitive domains, such as memory and decision-making.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="talks-and-slides">Talks and Slides:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/modes_Basel_2.html">External and Internal Modes in Perception</a></li> </ul> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Weilnhammer et al., PLOS Biology, 2023. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Weilnhammer et al., Current Biology, 2024. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Weilnhammer et al., Brain, 2024. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Veith Weilnhammer</name></author><category term="schizophrenia"/><category term="psychosis"/><category term="hallucinations"/><category term="ketamine"/><category term="HMM-GLM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[External and internal modes of inference.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality?</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality?"/><published>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/blog/consciousness/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2> <p>Conscious perception depends on the brain’s ability to resolve ambiguity in sensory signals. Our research examines how frontoparietal brain region — especially the <strong>inferior frontal cortex (IFC)</strong> and <strong>anterior insula</strong> — detect and resolve perceptual conflicts. We used neuroimaging, computational modeling, lesion studies, and brain stimulation to investigate how these systems contribute to a coherent experience of reality.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <h3 id="1-ifc-detects-and-resolves-conflict">1. IFC detects and resolves conflict</h3> <p>We showed that the inferior frontal cortex plays a causal role in resolving perceptual ambiguity<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Transient disruption of IFC activity via TMS slowed perceptual updates in bistable vision tasks, indicating that this region helps update conscious percepts in response to conflict.</p> <h3 id="2-insula-tracks-context-violations">2. Insula tracks context violations</h3> <p>We found that both temporal and spatial context violations activate a common network including the anterior insula and right IFC<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. These findings suggest a generalized mechanism for detecting when predictions fail, across multiple perceptual domains.</p> <h3 id="3-ifc-damage-reduces-perceptual-switching">3. IFC damage reduces perceptual switching</h3> <p>In stroke patients with IFC lesions, spontaneous perceptual switching during ambiguous visual tasks was reduced compared to controls<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>. This supports a causal role for IFC in generating perceptual updates and maintaining a dynamic conscious state.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="synthesis">Synthesis</h2> <p>Together, these studies suggest that conscious perception relies on frontoparietal systems that detect and resolve sensory conflicts. The IFC appears to be central to this process, in which it detects mismatches between input and expectation, and triggers perceptual updates that shape awareness.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="methods">Methods</h2> <p>We used a multi-method approach:</p> <ul> <li>Behavioral paradigms involving bistable perception.</li> <li>fMRI to identify prediction error responses.</li> <li>TMS to establish causal links between IFC activity and perceptual dynamics.</li> <li>Structural lesion mapping in stroke patients with focal IFC damage.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="implications">Implications</h2> <p>Our findings clarify how higher-order brain regions influence perception. They support predictive processing accounts of consciousness and highlight the IFC as a potential target for therapeutic interventions in disorders involving perceptual rigidity or instability.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <ul> <li>Developing real-time measures of prediction error and perceptual updating.</li> <li>Testing IFC-targeted brain stimulation to modulate conscious perception.</li> <li>Extending this framework to other cognitive domains such as memory and belief updating.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <h3 id="papers">Papers:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2021.04.043">IFC and perceptual conflict (Current Biology, 2021)</a></li> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.05.29.595872">Insula and general prediction errors (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/2024.08.24.609496">IFC lesions and perceptual dynamics (bioRxiv, 2024)</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="presentation">Presentation:</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/reveal/CCN.html">Is the IFC part of the NCC?</a></li> </ul> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Weilnhammer et al., Current Biology, 2021 <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Reichenbach et al., bioRxiv, 2024 <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Fritsch et al., bioRxiv, 2024 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Veith Weilnhammer</name></author><category term="consciousness"/><category term="perception"/><category term="inference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The role of frontoparietal networks in resolving sensory ambiguity.]]></summary></entry></feed>