<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-13T13:48:14+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Veith Weilnhammer. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Psychotherapy, Coaching &amp;amp; Counseling</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/psychotherapy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychotherapy, Coaching &amp;amp; Counseling"/><published>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/psychotherapy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/psychotherapy/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="mental-healthcare-when-and-where-you-need-it">Mental healthcare when and where you need it</h1> <p>My mission is to make evidence-based mental healthcare accessible to everyone. I offer online psychotherapy, coaching, counseling, and support for people experiencing mental health challenges.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="about-me">About Me</h2> <p>I am a board-certified psychiatrist and psychotherapist. I completed my clinical training at the Charité in Berlin. I trained in <strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</strong> and <strong>Systemic Psychotherapy</strong> at the Center for Psychotherapy, Humboldt University of Berlin. Here are some key principles and methods I draw upon:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT)</strong>: Evidence-based strategies to reframe unhelpful patterns of thought and behavior, manage stress, and develop more adaptive coping skills.</li> <li><strong>Mindfulness and Acceptance Techniques</strong>: Develop awareness, resilience, and compassion for oneself.</li> <li><strong>Systemic Therapy</strong>: Considers your concerns within the broader context of family, social, and professional systems.</li> <li><strong>Open Dialogue</strong>: A collaborative approach focusing on transparent communication and a shared decision-making process, especially helpful in crisis situations.</li> </ul> <p>I am passionate about digital technologies to better understand, predict, and improve mental health. If you would like more details about my work as a scientist and clinician, you can find my <a href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/assets/pdf/CV_Weilnhammer.pdf">CV here</a>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="range-of-services">Range of Services</h2> <p>If you’re experiencing a life crisis, stress-related concerns, or deeper mental health issues, <strong>online psychotherapy</strong> can be a flexible and effective solution. I provide confidential sessions via <strong>secure video calls</strong>, enabling you to receive support from the comfort of your own space.</p> <p>In addition to one-on-one therapy, I also offer:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Group Therapy</strong>: A safe, moderated space where clients can learn from each other’s experiences and practice new skills in a supportive environment.</li> <li><strong>Coaching &amp; Counseling</strong>: Tailored guidance for personal development, career challenges, or transitional life phases.</li> </ul> <p>My goal is to meet you where you are and ensure you have the resources and support you need. Please feel free to reach out to discuss which format (individual, group, or coaching) might best suit your situation. Availability for group therapy and coaching may vary, so contact me to learn more about open slots and scheduling options.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-to-expect-in-therapy">What to Expect in Therapy</h2> <p>During the first sessions, we will:</p> <ul> <li>Discuss your current concerns and personal goals.</li> <li>Explore relevant background information (e.g., medical and psychological history).</li> <li>Co-create a treatment plan that best fits your needs, which can include weekly or bi-weekly sessions.</li> </ul> <p>Each session typically runs <strong>50 minutes</strong> and may involve:</p> <ul> <li>Discussing recent experiences or changes in mood or perspective</li> <li>Identifying and challenging negative thought patterns or core beliefs</li> <li>Practicing new coping strategies</li> <li>Setting goals and homework to use between sessions</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="fees--insurance">Fees &amp; Insurance</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Self-Paying Clients</strong>: Please contact me directly for information about session fees or potential sliding-scale arrangements.</li> <li><strong>Insurance Coverage</strong>: Many health insurance providers offer partial or full reimbursement for therapy costs. Kindly check with your insurer about your specific plan and benefits.</li> </ul> <p>If cost is a concern, feel free to reach out — I’m committed to helping make care as accessible as possible.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="contact--booking">Contact &amp; Booking</h2> <p>To schedule an appointment or request more information, please send me an email: <a href="mailto:veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com">veith.weilnhammer@gmail.com</a></p> <hr/> <h3 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h3> <p>This website is for informational purposes only. It is not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. If you need immediate help or are experiencing a crisis, please contact a mental health care provider or the emergency services in your area.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pages"/><category term="psychotherapy"/><category term="mental-health"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn more about my psychotherapy approach, background, and how to book a session.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">External and internal modes of perception</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/external_internal_perception/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="External and internal modes of perception"/><published>2024-06-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/external_internal_perception</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/external_internal_perception/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="consciousness"/><category term="psychosis"/><category term="perception"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How does perception balance new infomration with prior knowledge?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Concepts and models of schizophrenia</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/concepts_schizophrenia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concepts and models of schizophrenia"/><published>2022-04-01T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/concepts_schizophrenia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/concepts_schizophrenia/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="schizophrenia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How has the understanding of schizophrenia changed over time?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The neural correlates of consciousness in health and in psychosis</title><link href="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/NCC_health_psychosis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The neural correlates of consciousness in health and in psychosis"/><published>2022-02-01T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/NCC_health_psychosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://veithweilnhammer.github.io/projects/NCC_health_psychosis/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="consciousness"/><category term="psychosis"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What are the mechanisms that construct our experience of reality, and how do they fail in psychosis?]]></summary></entry></feed>